Page סו Samech-Vav 66 and we start where do we start? We
start at the bottom of סה Samech-Hei עמוד ב Amud Beis and
we are...
no, are we 66 or 65?
We're 65.
No, we are 66, I'm sorry. I was right the first time.
Okay, alright. You know what they say: the last time I thought
I made a mistake, I was wrong. Okay, anyway, so bottom of
65, 65ב. Beis. רבי חנינא בר יוסף.
Rabbi Chanina
bar Yosef. So רבי חנינא בר יוסף Rabbi Chanina bar Yosef is
ten lines from the bottom. So what we talked about yesterday was
a case where the landlord was around and the renter was not
around and it said that as long as the landlord has the
right to move the renter around from one room to another
and then he also has presence and control and you can rent
from him.
And they made the decision without knowing the הלכה Halacha and then
they got the הלכה Halacha confirmed afterwards. Sort of reminds you of
that whole story about blowing the שופר Shofar in יבנה Yavneh and
then afterwards you know, you already set a precedent. But anyway, that
is very relevant for הלכות Halachos about making an עירוב Eruv and
renting from the city. And how does renting from the city work
if you're not renting from each individual homeowner and so on? And
so these issues and an apartment building, do you need an עירוב
Eruv in an apartment building? Does the fact that the landlord maybe
can't move you out of your apartment but he has presence in
it, he owns major appliances in it? These are very relevant for
practical aspects of הלכה, Halacha, maybe later. Okay, so let's take a
look. Now we get though to another story about a case that
occurred in an inn, in a... so let's take a look.
רבי חנינא בר יוסף, Rabbi Chanina bar Yosef, רבי חייא בר אבא,
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, איקלעו לההוא פונדק. Ikle'u
l'hahu pundak. They came to a certain inn, you know, that had
rented rooms and different rooms. דאתא נכרי מרי דפונדקא בשבתא. D'ata Nochri
Mari d'Pundaka b'Shabta.
Now the non-Jew who was the owner of the inn arrived on
שבת. Shabbos. So the basic assumption here is what happened was
they made an עירוב Eruv before on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos based
on the assumption, as you remember from the גמרא Gemara before, that
if the non-Jew is not present, I mean the גמרא Gemara presumed
a debate of תנאים Tannaim even if a Jew is not present,
but if a non-Jew is not present before שבת Shabbos begins, then
he does not create a problem. You can go ahead and make
an עירוב Eruv in the space, right? It's only if the non-Jew
is actually present there before שבת Shabbos begins. So presumably they rented
and they made an עירוב Eruv in the space and then lo
and behold on שבת, Shabbos, the non-Jew arrived. So his presence now
is considered to have destroyed the עירוב Eruv because you assess it
as if it would have been before שבת Shabbos and you need
to do a שכירות. Sechirus. So even though you were okay making
the עירוב Eruv before שבת, Shabbos, now that he's here you have
a problem.
Wait, did they do שכירות? Sechirus? They were in an inn.
Presumably there was no other... what... wait a second...
presumably there was no other non-Jews so they did שכירות Sechirus from
the individual non-Jews that had the other rooms, but the non-Jewish owner
who had his own room came. So effectively the point is is
that one of the non-Jews who had a house who wasn't there
and wasn't a problem arrived on שבת Shabbos and created a problem.
Okay, so and there's this long תוספות Tosafot that tries to figure
out this issue
about when do we say that because it was good before שבת
Shabbos began, it remains good and when do we say that it
gets reversed when a problem arises? But here the גמרא Gemara is
assuming it gets reversed. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אמרו מהו למיגר מיניה? Amru mahu l'meigar minei? Can we rent from
him on שבת Shabbos itself and fix the problem right now on
שבת? Shabbos? שוכר כמהרב דמי? Socher k'me'arev dami? Do we say that
renting is like making an
עירוב? Eruv? מה מערב מבעוד יום, Mah me'arev m'be'od yom, the same
way you can only make an עירוב Eruv from before שבת, Shabbos,
אף שוכר מבעוד יום, af socher m'be'od yom, so the שכירות Sechirus
that you do that has, you know, with the non-Jew has to
take effect before
שבת? Shabbos? או דלמא שוכר כמבטל רשות דמי? O dilma socher k'mevatel
reshus dami? That a שוכר socher is like... because the שוכר, socher,
מבטל רשות mevatel reshus are the two tricks, you know, the two
strategies, devices that are used when you cannot do an actual עירוב.
Eruv. So מבטל רשות mevatel reshus could work like one of the
Jews, it was just Jews and he forgot to make his עירוב,
Eruv, right? And now you realize on שבת Shabbos so he מבטל
mevatel his רשות, reshus, that would be an easy scenario. There are
other cases, but classic מבטל רשות mevatel reshus means that something happened
on שבת Shabbos and you have to fix it and the way
you fix it, because you can't make an עירוב, Eruv, is you
do ביטול רשות. bitul reshus. שוכר Socher we know is the primary
strategy used for a non-Jew and how you deal with the non-Jew's,
you know, domain, רשות, reshus, on שבת. Shabbos. So does it work
like... because it's like a strategy around עירוב, Eruv, does it work
like מבטל רשות mevatel reshus that you can do it even on
שבת Shabbos itself? Or is it a way of effecting עירוב, Eruv,
that's the way I'll reframe the גמרא Gemara's question, with the non-Jew,
right? So therefore since it's part of... it's not like an alternative
to עירוב, Eruv, it's similar to עירוב, Eruv, it's a way of
effecting... effecting the unification of the courtyard and therefore you have to
do it from before שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So that's the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s question, does the שכירות s'chirus, *secherus*, we know עירוב eruv. *eruv*
has to be before שבת Shabbos? *Shabbos*, we know ביטול רשות bittul
reshus. *bitul reshus* can happen on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* itself when you
realize you've got a problem, a Jew can be מבטל m'vatel *mevatel*
his רשות reshus *reshus*, and the question is שכירות s'chirus. *secherus* from
a non-Jew, is that before שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* or on שבת Shabbos?
*Shabbos*? So now it's on שבת shabbos *Shabbos*, are you allowed to
do the שכירות schirus *secherus* on שבת Shabbos? *Shabbos* itself? So of
course the question that my guy is going to ask is since
when are you allowed to rent on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*? Okay fine,
so we'll take a little look at this תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* where
יפה עשיתם ששכרתם *yafeh
asitem she-sechartem* on ס"ו עמוד א' amud aleph, *samekh vav amud aleph*
near the bottom there, about 20 lines from the bottom on דמי
*dami*, the one-line tiny little תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says לא דמי למקח
וממכר דאסור בשבת דלא הוי אלא כמתנה בעלמא שאין עושין אלא להתיר
טלטול *lo dami le-mikach u-mimkar de-asur be-Shabbos de-lo havei ela ke-matanah be-alma
she-ein asin ela le-hattir tiltul*. Which means the whole thing is a
ritual, we know it's all not a real rental, we do it
even less than a שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah *shaveh proutah* we said
the other day, we don't really, you know, the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
spoke about it being a שכירות schirus, רעועה *secherus reuah*, so nobody
has a problem of actually doing the rental for הלכות שבת Shabbos
*Hilchos Shabbos*. The question is will it be effective in order to
solve this problem? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
מה מבטל m'vatel רשות reshus אף שוכר socher
*ma mevatel reshus af socher*, so מה
מבטל mevatel רשות reshus אפילו בשבת אף שוכר אפילו בשבת *ma mevatel
reshus afilu be-Shabbos af socher afilu be-Shabbos*. So what's the story? Can
you do the שכירות sechirut *secherus* on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*? So four
lines from the bottom, רבי חנינא בר יוסף אמר נשכור *Rabbi Chanina
bar Yosef amar niscor*, let's rent it. רב יוסף Rav Yosef אמר
רב אסי אמר לא נשכור *Rav Yosef amar Rav Assi amar lo
niscor*, let's not rent it. אמר לו רבי חייא בר אבא נסמוך
על דברי זקן ונשכור *amar lo Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba nismoch al divrei zaken ve-niscor*,
let's rely on the elder, let's rely on רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina*
and let's rent, right? So it's
for those that are familiar with that famous משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* in
ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* about do they do תקיעת שופר *tekias shofar*
after חורבן בית המקדש *churban Beis HaMikdash* in יבנה *Yavneh* on שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos*, you know? So רבן יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai* said נתקע *niska*, בני בתירא *Bnei Beseira* said, you know, לא
נתקע *lo niska*. So he said let's just blow and we'll talk
about it afterwards. So anyway, so then they blew and it was
too late. So anyway, okay, so נסמוך על דברי זקן ונשכור *nismoch
al divrei zaken ve-niscor*. עשו שאלה ליה לרבי יוחנן *asu shaylah leh
le-Rabbi Yochanan*, they came and they asked רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi
Yochanan*, meaning they did that, they rented it, and then after שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* they asked רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* what should
we have done? אמר להם יפה עשיתם ששכרתם *amar lahem yafeh asitem
she-sechartem*, oh that was a good decision. Okay, and again, you know,
presumably A: they maybe really assumed that was correct, or you know,
as the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* in the previous one is they didn't
know but it was a דרבנן *derabanan*, it was a ספק *safek*,
and we always say הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב *halacha k-divrei ha-meikel be-eruv*,
and therefore they figured that it was good enough to rely on.
So, תו נרדא *Tav Narda*, so the נרדאי *Nardai* was astounded about
this. וכי אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan הכי *ve-chi amar Rabbi Yochanan
hachi*, did רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* really say this? והאמר רבי יוחנן
שוכר כמערב דמי *ve-ha-amar Rabbi Yochanan socher ke-meariv dami*, he actually is,
it was known to have said that the renting is like making
an עירוב eruv, *eruv*. So a renting from the non-Jew is like
making, it's like the עירוב eruv. *eruv* itself. So מאי לאו מה
מערב m'areiv. מבעוד יום אף שוכר מבעוד יום *mai lav ma meariv
me-voad yom af socher me-voad yom*, does it not mean the same
way you have to do the עירוב eruv, *eruv* from the day
before, you have to do שכירות sechirut *secherus* from the day before?
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* said לא מה מערב m'areiv אפילו בפחות משוה פרוטה
אף שוכר אפילו בפחות משוה פרוטה *lav ma meariv afilu be-pachos mi-shaveh
proutah af socher afilu be-pachos mi-shaveh proutah*. Now we're going to have
a whole list of comparisons
which are all going to be לקולא *le-kula*. Okay? The same way
an עירוב eruv. *eruv* you can do it even if the bread
is less than a פרוטה *proutah*, right? If you contribute bread, it
can be even if it's less than a פרוטה *proutah*. So therefore
also the שכירות *secherus* less than a פרוטה *proutah*, that's the stuff
we talked about earlier. ומה מערב m'areiv אפילו שכיר ולקיטו *u-ma meariv
afilu sochir ve-lakito*, and what's the story when you make an עירוב
eruv *eruv* that if a Jewish sort of, you know, is in
the employ of the non-Jew and is a hired hand and works
on the property, so he can actually be considered as if he
were the owner and make an עירוב eruv. *eruv*. So the עירוב
eruv *eruv* can be done even by the שכיר ולקיטו *sochir ve-lakito*.
אף שוכר אפילו שכיר ולקיטו *af socher afilu sochir ve-lakito*. So let's
say the hired hand is not a Jew, let's say the hired
hand is a non-Jew. So you can rent from the hired hand
the same way you can rent from the actual, you know, owner
of the property itself. Again, making it more easy
to involve that property and make that property part of the עירוב
eruv *eruv*. So that's comparison number two לקולא *le-kula*. And comparison number
three: ומה מערב me'arev חמישה ששרויין בחצר אחת אחד מערב על ידי
כולן *u-ma meariv chamishah she-shruyun be-chatzer echad echad me-ariv al yedei kulan*,
and the story by עירוב eruv *eruv* is let's say you have
two courtyards like we discussed yesterday and we're going to discuss again
today that are open one into the other and they want to
make a big עירוב eruv, *eruv* between them. So courtyard A makes
an עירוב eruv, *eruv* and courtyard B makes an עירוב eruv. *eruv*,
they make their individual עירוב eruv, *eruv*, and then somebody from courtyard
A goes and brings the עירוב eruv, *eruv* of A into B.
They would not make a new עירוב eruv, *eruv*, they would just
deposit their עירוב eruv *eruv* into the other courtyard and that would
be seen as a way of making an עירוב eruv *eruv* for
both courtyards combined. So one person, so you have five people living
in courtyard A and one person can go ahead and represent them
and bring their עירוב eruv *eruv* to B and make a unified
עירוב eruv, *eruv*. So that's true about עירוב eruv, *eruv*. שוכר נמי
*socher nami*, so by He says as well, we have a similar
type of leniency. חמישה ששרויים בחצר אחת, אחד שוכר ידי כולן. echad
socher y'dei kulan. Let's say you have five people that are living
in a courtyard and one non-Jew, so one person can represent the
whole
rest of the courtyard to do the rental from the non-Jew. Because
again, it's not like it's rented to an individual member of the
courtyard, it's like it's rented to the collective, right? To make it
part of the עירוב. eruv. So therefore one person can represent the
collective. So you have all of these comparisons and they're all to
be lenient but not to be strict and say you have to
take care of it from ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. And רש"י Rashi
points out, if you look at the first רש"י, Rashi, לאו ממר
ואפילו פשיטא, Lo mar v'afilu p'shita, he says דכולה אקשינהו לרבי יוחנן
ולא לחומרא דכל בעירוב להקל. D'kula kshinu m'Rabbi Yochanan v'lo l'chumra d'kol
b'eruv l'hakel. רש"י Rashi says suddenly a שפת ווארט s'fas vort out
of that. So we interpret everything leniently. So if we're going to
make the comparison, we're going to make it for the lenient purposes,
not for the strict ones.
I just want to understand, so the reason it's not a problem
on שבת Shabbos is twofold? Because it's a ritual and it's פחות
משוה פרוטה? pachos mishaveh prutah? Or is it because it's the ritual,
it would have been more than שוה פרוטה it would have been
a problem? Which means let's say I...
תוספות Tosafot, does not emphasize the פחות משוה פרוטה. pachos mishaveh prutah.
So
others might, you know, but תוספות Tosafot is not emphasizing that as
significant. I just threw that in to be a further demonstration. Now
the גמרא Gemara. said even if it was a real שכירות, it
could work from a non-Jew with פחות משוה פרוטה. pachos mishaveh prutah.
So according to that earlier גמרא, Gemara it's not a good demonstration,
it's not relevant to the issue of whether it's like real or
ritual.
So what do you mean? It's no bearing on, let's say I
wanted to buy all your... let's say you decided to sell me
your apartment for פחות משוה פרוטה pachos mishaveh prutah on שבת? Shabbos.
Yeah, yeah, don't, no, no, no. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. So that's the answer. Okay, so we did it, we solved
the problem with שכירות. Now the גמרא, Gemara not stated anywhere here,
but it's going to be clear in the next line, you would
have thought, okay, we made an עירוב, eruv came along the non-Jew,
he came home on שבת, Shabbos. we had a rent from him,
and that solved the problem. So you would think that by itself
solves the problem. We rented from him and now we're back to
where we were before, we have a good עירוב. eruv But רש"י
Rashi and תוספות, these long רש"י Rashi תוספות explain because it's going
to be clear in the גמרא, gemara that actually what happened is
once he came and he ruined the עירוב, eruv, then we no
longer have an עירוב. eruv Because all I did... the עירוב eruv,
has to be the one that was in effect from before שבת.
Shabbos, And that was destroyed and it can't re-emerge. So now that
he came, fine, יישר כח, yasher koach, we rented from him, but
we still don't have an עירוב. eruv So what's implicit but not
stated but is going to be made more explicit in a minute
is that after we rented from him, as it were got him
out of the picture, we still have to solve the problem. And
how do you solve the problem if you have a courtyard that
didn't do an עירוב eruv, on שבת? Shabbos. You do ביטול bittul
רשות. reshus That basically everybody in the courtyard says to one guy,
we waive our rights to you. And therefore it's all like it's
just one guy. Which basically means that you can carry in the
courtyard, which actually could have been done beforehand for things that started
in the courtyard. You don't need an עירוב eruv. for that. The
basic purpose for the עירוב eruv, is carrying from the houses into
the courtyard and the courtyard into the houses. So really by doing
a ביטול bittul, to this one guy, all it really allows you
to do now is that one guy can carry from his house
out into the courtyard and vice versa. So you wonder even why
it's even worth the effort, but okay. Anyways, so presumably what happened
is after they were שוכר from the non-Jew, they did a ביטול,
bittul. which isn't being said. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this:
תהי בה רבי אליעזר. Tohi bah Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
was תהי. tohi. Now before the גמרא gemara says תהו, tahu, which
means that they were astounded, like בתמיה. bitmiya. תהי tahi actually is
a different word which means he smelled it. Okay, which means he
was like (sniffing sound) he was like trying to figure out what
was going on here.
So אמר רבי זירא: Amar Rabbi Zeira: מאי תהיאי דרבי אליעזר? Mai
tahi'ei d'Rabbi Eliezer? What was רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer smelling? So what
was he trying to figure out about this case? So אמר רב
ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, so and maybe it was like, maybe it
was like you know rhetorical: What's he so bothered with? So אמר
רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshet: גברא רבא כרבי זירא לא ידע מאי
תהיאי דרבי אליעזר? Gavra raba k'Rabbi Zeira lo yada mai tahi'ei d'Rabbi
Eliezer? So a great person like רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira couldn't understand
what was bothering רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, what he was sort of
you know trying to figure out? So קקשיא ליה דשמואל רביה, k'kasha
leh d'Shmuel rabeih, he's bothered by שמואל's Shmuel statement himself. דאמר שמואל,
D'amar Shmuel, because שמואל Shmuel says. Right? And the previous גמרא gemara
by the way was said by נהרדעי, Nehardaei,
right? Anyway, נהרדעי Nehardaei was just saying... anyway forget that point. Okay
anyway he was... he was trying to figure out the relevance
of שמואל's Shmuel statement. דאמר שמואל: כל מקום שאוסרין ומערבין מבטלין. da'amar
Shmuel kol מקום שאוסרין ומערבין מבטלין. Any place where the people will
create a problem, forbid on one another, and they could make an
עירוב, eruv you can do ביטול. bitul. Now what does that mean?
If you remember again the point is is that and we're once
again going to get to our wonderful scenario here with these two
courtyards, where am I? Anyway in the normal scenario, let's let's talk
about a normal courtyard.
Okay
if you have a normal courtyard, here's your courtyard and you have
your multiple houses. If one guy refuses to make the עירוב, eruv
right? Does it work for everybody else? No. You have... everybody has
to participate. אוסרין. osrin. אוסרין osrin means any individual can create a
problem for anybody else, okay? Now, if they want to, they can
make an עירוב. eruv. That's מערב. So
because they can create a problem and if they want to they
can create an עירוב, eruv then if he didn't create an עירוב,
eruv, if they didn't do an עירוב, eruv right? Then the way
you can solve it is you can do ביטול. bitul. You can
waive your property rights and then it all works, okay? So you
need these two. The relevance of each of these basically means that
you are seen as one unit, okay? The fact that your presence
creates a problem for somebody else means that you're all in this
together. מערבין m'arvin also is another measure of the fact that you're
all can be unified and there's the potential of being brought together.
So if you have these two qualities then you're basically all one
unit then חז"ל chazal allowed you if you were stuck on שבת
Shabbos because somebody forgot or some problem arose, way of solving it
is this concept of ביטול. bitul. So כל מקום שאוסרין ומערבין מבטלין.
Kol makom she'osrin u'm'arvin m'vatlin. Therefore, if you have both of those
qualities, therefore מבטלין. m'vatlin. Now we're going to see cases where you
have one and not the other.
Meaning if you didn't do מערב so you do a ביטול.
bitul If you didn't do the מערב you still do the ביטול
bitul but only in a scenario where you could have done עירוב
eruv. and where you had an אוסרין osrin where your presence of
of everybody made a problem for everyone else. If somebody's presence was
irrelevant then he's not part of that group. And we're going to
see, we're going to see what those cases are, okay? Don't start,
don't start speculating, the גמרא Gemara will spell it out. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
And this is eventually going to lead to a problem of this
case of the non-Jew, how did the ביטול bitul work in this
case of the non-Jew? Okay, so we'll see, that's where we're going,
but let's see how we get there. So the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: כל מקום שאוסרין ומערבין מבטלין. kol makom she'osrin u'm'arvin m'vatlin. מערבין
ואין אוסרין, m'arvin v'ein osrin, if you do an עירוב eruv. but
you would not have been created a presence, your presence would not
have created a problem, or the opposite, אוסרין ואין מערבין, osrin v'ein
m'arvin, you create a presence but עירוב eruv. is not possible, אין
מבטלין, ein m'vatlin, ביטול bitul. does not work. Now we're going to
explain these scenarios, okay? כל מקום
שאוסרין ומערבין מבטלין,
kol makom
she'osrin u'm'arvin m'vatlin. any place where you both for- make it forbidden
and you there's the possibility of doing an עירוב, eruv. then you
can do ביטול. bitul כגון, k'gon, now obviously the scenario I gave
you was obvious, so you don't need to say that. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to give a a more interesting case. כגון
k'gon שתי חצירות, sh'tei chatzeirot, the classic two courtyards,
זו לפנים מזו, zo lifnim m'zo, one inside the other. מערבין ואין-
m'arvin v'ein- okay, that would be- now what does that mean? So
here's your case, right, the case that we had yesterday. Here's your
street, right, you have the two courtyards A and B, forget the
non-Jew right now. So in this case regarding B, okay, if A
is אוסר oser on B, the presence of A, right, the presence
of this guy, okay, there we'll call forget the Jew, okay, we'll
call him A, A1 and A2, okay, this is B1 and B2,
so the presence of these people here in A, right, create a
problem on B, they're אוסר oser because as we saw, since they
pass through B and if they don't make an עירוב, eruv. then
the fact that they have rights that they go through B, that
creates a presence of B. And if they want to, they could
all make one one עירוב. eruv. So therefore if one of these
guys, let's say, forgot, right, he could just do ביטול bitul and
that'll solve the problem because effectively, again, that's enough to be considered
one unit. Now we're going to actually see that not everybody agrees
to this case, but that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying right
now, that the fact that they are אוסר oser is enough to
make them one unit. Let me just give you a sense about
why this is a חידוש chiddush because in all- an alternative opinion
we're going to hear in a min- in a minute as we
turn the page is you can't be מבטל מרשות לרשות. m'vatel me'reshut
l'reshut. You can only be מבטל mevatel to the people of your
own courtyard, you can't be מבטל mevatel to the people of another
courtyard. So if this guy forgot, if A1 forgot, he can't do
a ביטול bitul that helps out B. That's going to be- yeah,
that's going to be an alternative opinion. So the logic of שמואל
Shmuel is he says no, look, since in theory you could all
make one עירוב eruv and because you standing out creates problems for
B, that makes you enough seen as one basic group and therefore
in that case they allowed ביטול bitul. as a solution to the
problem. Okay, so that's that case of אוסרין ומערבין מבטלין. osrin u'm'arvin
m'vatlin. Now let's look at cases that don't work.
מערבין ואין אוסרין m'arvin v'ein osrin אין מבטלין. ein m'vatlin. If you
could do an עירוב eruv but you would not make it forbidden
without an עירוב, eruv then you can't do ביטול. bitul, כגון k'gon
שתי חצירות ופתח אחד ביניהן. sh'tei chatzeirot u'petach echad beineihen. So that's
the other case. That's the case where you've got here, we'll erase
this.
Takes a case where you've got this main street and you have
these two courtyards, right, each one opens up into the street.
Okay, so you've got your A and B, but they are not,
don't impact one another because you have an access to the street
separately, right, so there's no need of one to go through. So
can they make one עירוב eruv, together? Yes, if they want. Okay,
if one of these, if this guy is not having an עירוב,
eiruv, does that- Does that hurt B? That affect B? No.
Only if they want to go into A.
Well, yes, but there, the fact that they stuck out does not
affect them here. So that means the fact that they don't create
a problem means they're not really all in it together. They're not
all one unit. And because of that, if A let's
say didn't make a what do you call it, if somebody in
A didn't make an עירוב eiruv, and he wants to do a
ביטול, bitul let's say everybody in A wants to be מבטל mevatel
their רשות to B so that B come into A. Okay, you
got it? They didn't do a joint עירוב, eiruv, but A wants
to say to B now we want you to be able to
carry your stuff, we're all going to be מבטל mivatel our רשות
to you. No, I'm sorry. B is too much of a distinct
entity that we do not allow this fiction of ביטול bitul to
work. We allow the fiction of ביטול bitul when it's basically one
entity, not when it's a distinct entity. Okay, so because here although
they could become one, they don't have to be one, they're not
אוסרין, osrin, therefore A cannot do a ביטול bitul to B and
vice versa.
So what you need then is an עירוב.
eiruv If they wanted to carry from B to A they had
to do an עירוב, eiruv of B, and if they forgot ביטול
bitul is not an option.
Okay, so that's that case.
Okay, so אוסרין ואין מבטלין... osrin ve'ein mevatlin... sorry,
אוסרין ואין מערבין ואין מבטלין osrin ve'ein me'arvin ve'ein mevatlin where you
create a problem but an עירוב eiruv, isn't possible. לספויי מאי? lasfuyei
mai? What's that scenario? That's the flip, where your presence is a
problem, so you have some impact, but you're not normally unified because
an עירוב eiruv isn't an option. What's that case?
לאו לאתויי נכרי? lav le'atuyei nachri? Must be a non-Jew. Non-Jew, his
presence... he can't be part of the עירוב. eiruv You would think
in a normal case he can't be part of the עירוב eiruv
because שכירות doesn't work... okay, because you need שכירות, you normally don't
have עירוב, eiruv but his presence is a problem. So you could
have said every case of a non-Jew is that way, and we'll
never allow ביטול bitul to work in the presence of a non-Jew,
although you never do ביטול bitul to the non-Jew, but anyway we
won't allow it in that case. But the גמרא Gemara actually modifies
that. The גמרא Gemara says like
this: דאתי מאתמול לא גרמי מאתמול. de'asa me'esmol lo garmei me'esmol. If
he came yesterday, we could have rented yesterday, and therefore what does
that mean? That means that if he actually is considered to be
in the category of מערבין me'arvin if he was around yesterday. The
potential of renting from him makes him considered part of, you could
have used his presence and you could have rented from him. So
that's in the type of מערבין me'arvin category. So therefore in that
case ביטול bitul would work. Now I gotta tell you, it's a
little bit confusing here because in these cases where we're saying ביטול
bitul, works, it means the guy... because they create a problem, it's
one of them forgot, he can do ביטול, bitul, right? Here, because
the non-Jew creates a problem, the non-Jew isn't doing ביטול, bitul you're
not doing ביטול bitul to the non-Jew, the presence of the non-Jew
in the courtyard created a problem, therefore we can now do ביטול
bitul. with the rest of us here. It's a little bit of
a funny... the equation is not... what?
What do they do with the non-Jew then when he comes on
שבת?
Shabbos Well, they rent from him to get him out of the
picture again, or they rented from him before שבת. Shabbos So basically
it would be saying, let's say we rented from the non-Jew before
שבת but we forgot to do our עירוב eiruv. or one guy
sat out on his עירוב. eiruv Then he can go ahead and
do a ביטול. bitul It's a little funny because the non-Jew isn't
the party that's part of the ביטול bitul here as opposed to
it is in the other cases. But if he were around before
שבת, he would be מערבין, me'arvin, so it would be possible. So
it must be the point of saying this scenario of אוסרין ואין
מערבין osrin ve'ein me'arvin is exactly the case we're talking about. Okay,
let's take a look as we turn the page. אלא לאו, ela
lav, it must be דאתי בשבתא. de'asa beshabsa. It's our scenario, that
the non-Jew arrived on שבת, and he's considered to be a case
of אין מערבין, ein me'arvin, אוסרין osrin yes, he showed up he
created the problem, אין מערבין ein me'arvin because he wasn't around before
שבת to be part of the equation. It's funny, but before שבת
he wasn't a problem because he wasn't around. Anyway, and so now
you can't be מערב right now. So it's again it's a funny
application to this scenario that normally he would be considered מערבין, me'arvin,
now he's not. And it's also funny because the ביטול bitul is
not relevant, is not being done to him, it's between the Jews
of the courtyard themselves that have not made an עירוב. eiruv, Anyway,
ותניא אוסרין ואין מערבין ואין מבטלין. vesanya osrin ve'ein me'arvin ve'ein mevatlin.
So שמע מינה. shma mina. So you can infer that. So you
see that according to שמואל׳ס Shmuel's principle, this idea of ביטול bitul.
shouldn't work when the non-Jew shows up on שבת. So that's the
whole point. So again, the case was the non-Jew showed up on
שבת. You could have said he showed up on שבת, created a
problem, we just ruled you're allowed to rent from him, you rented
from him, the problem went away. But the גמרא Gemara assumes without
ever saying that no, even now that we've rented from him the
problem went away, the only way we can now solve it is
to do ביטול. bitul And based on this idea of שמואל, Shmuel,
which in the abstract makes a lot of sense, if you want
to allow ביטול bittul which is this fiction, then it will only
be if you're really considered to be all in it together. But
based on that, the גמרא Gemara said that last case of אוסרין
ואין מערבין osrin ve'ein me'arvin addresses is our case. And in this
case because of the... non-Jew somehow even though you've now had the
ביטול bittul. because you did שכירות somehow you still can't do עירוב.
eiruv, Okay so the גמרא Gemara is reject, can't do ביטול. bittul
So the גמרא Gemara is rejecting the possibility in this scenario
of that שכירות followed by ביטול bittul. would actually work.
So the question on everybody's was what about
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan and? Right. So the גמרא Gemara says but
according to שמואל Shmuel this shouldn't work. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
accepts that, that that's implicit in שמואל's Shmuel statement. But we're not
done yet. אמר ליה Amar lei אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef,
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said: לא שמיע לי הא שמעתא. Lo shemi'a
li ha shema'ta. You know what, I never heard this teaching of
שמואל, Shmuel, right, that, that you know you need these two criteria
and when you have these two criteria you could always do ביטול.
bittul. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said: את
אמרת ניהלן. At amrat neih lan. What do you mean? You, you
told us this position of שמואל Shmuel because we know that רב
יוסף Rav Yosef, got ill and forgot things that he had learned
and taught. So אביי Abaye said: You actually taught us this position
of שמואל Shmuel of these two criteria of אוסרין ואין מערבין osrin
ve-ein me'arvin והא אמרת ניהלן ve-ha amrat neih lan and you told
it to us relevant to the following case.
דאמר שמואל: D'amar Shmuel: אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר ein bittul reshut
mi-chatzer le-chatzer ואין ביטול רשות בחורבה. ve-ein bittul reshut be-chorba. You can't
do ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר. bittul reshut mi-chatzer le-chatzer.
That's exactly this case, okay?
If A, if somebody in A forgot they can't waive their whatever.
If they don't go together with B they can't waive their right
to be allowed to carry into A. Or presumably we'll see this
case too. They can't be מערבין, me'arvin, they can't do ביטול. bittul?
You see מחצר לחצר. mi-chatzer le-chatzer. And a completely unrelated, not completely
unrelated but anyway, unrelated to our issues is a ביטול בחורבה bittul
be-chorba is doing a ביטול בחורבה. bittul be-chorba. There you have a
חורבה chorba which is an alley, okay, as opposed to a חצר
chatzer or a מבוי. mavoi. And here, you know, the back ends
of the houses, the front ends are here but the back ends
of the houses open into this alleyway. Okay and so you want
to carry in the alleyway on שבת. Can't do it so you
do an עירוב. eiruv But you forgot to do an עירוב. eiruv
Can you do ביטול? bittul Okay, so why not? Why should it
be different? If you want all the houses open in there you
want to. But the point is is that this ביטול bittul. is
a fiction and they allowed it for a courtyard which is where
you really do most of any, you know, the normal types of
carrying or using of objects you need to do is in the
courtyard. So because of that sort of degree of need of being
able to use the courtyard they allowed you this fiction of ביטול.
bittul They did not allow you the fiction of ביטול bittul for
purposes of using a backyard, a back alleyway. Okay so that's the
חורבה, chorba, unrelated. You'd have to do עירוב. eiruv, Okay but that
idea of חורבה chorba is unrelated to us, what's related to us
is you can't do ביטול מחצר לחצר. bittul mi-chatzer le-chatzer. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ואין ביטול רשות בחורבה ve-ein bittul reshut
be-chorba והא אמרת לה לן. ve-ha amrat la lan. So that was
a statement of שמואל Shmuel and then you, you רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef you said to us regarding this: כי אמר שמואל אין ביטול
רשות מחצר לחצר, ki amar Shmuel ein bittul reshut mi-chatzer le-chatzer, wait
a minute, when did שמואל Shmuel say that you can't do from
one courtyard to the other? לא אמרן אלא שתי חצירות ופתח אחד
ביניהן. Lo aman ela shetei chatzeros u-pesach echad beneihen.
That's the example I gave you where they both open individually into
the רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabbim, so they're to some degree unrelated. They
don't have to, you know, do an עירוב eiruv together. אבל זו
לפנים מזו, Aval zo lifnim mi-zo,
but if one is inside the other, this case where A, if
B wants to carry they must do an עירוב eiruv together with
A, then A is אוסר oser on B. So in that case
מבטלין. me-vattelin. So that they could do ביטול bittul and the reason
is presumably because of this other statement of שמואל Shmuel which is
כל מקום שאוסרין ואין מערבין kol makom she-osrin ve-ein me'arvin then you
can do ביטול bittul it's considered one unified group. What you see
out of all of this is that this idea of ביטול bittul
is a fiction. It's a way of solving problems that could have
been, should have been taken care of presumably another way through, through
doing an עירוב eiruv and so on. They allowed it under certain
circumstances. You see the emphasis of only allowing it in a חצר
chatzer and not in a חורבה chorba is, you know, a sense
of there's a need to make this work, so we're going to
allow this fiction if essentially you're all defined as, you know, fundamentally
your sense of being one unit is already there. You're defined as
one group and then we will sort of allow the ביטול bittul
to the other members of the group. That's sort of the context
in which you can allow the fiction, but not to somebody that
fundamentally is not part of you, that far we will not stretch
the fiction. Okay, so that's what you said, you told us that
teaching from שמואל Shmuel exactly to distinguish between these two cases. So
now the גמרא Gemara. goes on: אמר
ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef said back to אביי: Abaye: אנא אמינא משמיה דשמואל? ana amina
mi-shmei de-Shmuel? עדי
נביא לי? Adi nabi li? Did I say that in the name
of שמואל? Shmuel? והא אמר שמואל: ve-ha amar Shmuel: אין לנו בעירובין
אלא לשון משנתנו. ein lan be-eruvin ela li-shon mishnatenu.
That when it comes to עירובין eruvin we stick to the language
of the משנה. Mishnah And therefore what does that mean? Presumably it
means אנשי חצר ולא אנשי חצירות. anshei chatzer ve-lo anshei chatzeros. Now
this is not שמואל's Shmuel statement, this is רב יוסף's Rav Yosef
interpretation. We're going to see a משנה that talks about ביטול bittul?
that says the people of the חצר, chatzer, right, what's the standard
case of ביטול? bittul Right, the standard case of ביטול bitul is,
right, is basically one of these guys forgot, okay, and one of
them forgot and therefore all of these guys made
an עירוב, eiruv, this guy... to
be מבטל mivatel. *mevatel* one to the other. So he says Abba,
one minute, שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says we stick to the language of
the משנה *Mishna*. So the משנה *Mishna* says אנשי חצר chatzar *anshei
chatzer*, which would mean not אנשי חצרות *anshei chatzerot*. When there are
two חצרות *chatzerot* involved, you can't do ביטול bitul, *bittul* from one
to the other. So a stricter position than שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*. Right,
he said, he was saying יוסף *Yosef* would be okay with שמואל
Shmuel. *Shmuel*, excuse me, would be okay with this because אוסרין ומערבין
מבטלין osrin umearvin mevatlin, *osrin u'm'arvin mevatlin*, but no, from the fact
that it says אנשי חצר chatzer *anshei chatzer* that's to tell us
any time there are two courtyards involved you can't do ביטול bitul.
*bittul* one to the other. Okay. So how could you say that
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says you could do ביטול bitul *bittul* in that
case where how could I have said, whatever, how could I have
said that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says you could do ביטול bitul *bittul*
if שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* also says we stick to the language of
the משנה *Mishna* and that should never allow ביטול bitul *bittul* from
one חצר chatzer *chatzer* to the other? So אנשי חצר chatzer. ולא
אנשי חצרות *anshei chatzer v'lo anshei chatzerot*. So אמר ליה *amar leh*,
he said back to him, כי אמרת לן אין לנו בעירובין אלא
כלשון משנתנו *ki amarta lan ein lanu b'eruvin ela k'lashon mishnateinu*. So
now he's correcting רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* on another teaching
of his. רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef*, when you told us
that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* said you got to stick to the language
of the משנה *Mishna*, he did not mean on every single משנה
*Mishna* that appears in עירובין eiruvin *Eruvin*. He was responding to one
particular משנה *Mishna*. Which particular משנה *Mishna* was שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel* responding
to? So he says הכא אמרת לן *hacha amarta lan* on the
following משנה *Mishna*: שהמבואין לחצרות כחצר לבתים *sheha-mavu'in l'chatzerot k'chatzer l'battim*, that
there's a משנה *Mishna* that makes an analogy, right?
And this is, right the great sort of, you know, what I've
been telling you from day one, right? There you have your, your
you know whatever, your מבוי *mavoi*, your main court,
your alley of the street, and here are your חצרות *chatzers* and
each חצר *chatzer* has houses. So when you want to unify a
חצר *chatzer*, that's called עירובי חצרות *eruvei chatzerot*,
but when you want to unify a מבוי *mavoi*, that's called שיתוף
מבואות *shituf mavo'ot*. And the משנה *Mishna* says that it's a similar
like you know when we used to do our SAT questions, right?
What are those called? A is to B as B is to
C. Okay, so the houses are to the courtyard, right? The same
relationship as the courtyards are to the מבוי *mavoi*, and those are
the units that get together to make a שיתוף מבואות *shituf mavo'ot*.
So שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel* says אין לנו אלא כלשון משנתנו *ein lanu
ela k'lashon mishnateinu*. What's the relevance of that? The relevance of that
is because it used the plural...
what's the language? המבואין לחצרות *ha-mavu'in l'chatzerot*... he says that the same
that for to do a שיתוף מבואות *shituf mavo'ot* you need there
to be חצרות *chatzerot*, you need there to be חצרות *chatzerot* two
and each חצר *chatzer* has to have בתים *battim*. So you need
two courtyards, each courtyard having two houses to constitute an official courtyard
at least in order to do it. So when שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*
says we have to be precise to the language of the משנה
*Mishna*, it was not a universal statement. It was a דיוק *diyuk*
on one particular משנה *Mishna* to say that you need two courtyards
and two houses. Okay, but when it comes to this issue that
the people of the חצר *chatzer* can make an
עירוב eiruv *eruv*, I mean to do ביטול bitul *bittul*, שמואל Shmuel
*Shmuel* would say under the right circumstances you could even do ביטול
bitul *bittul* from one courtyard to the next. Okay, so we're back
to שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*'s statement, which is that in this case you
can do ביטול bitul *bittul* from one רשות *reshus* to the next
because it's אוסרין ומערבין מבטלין osrin umearvin mevatlin. *osrin u'm'arvin mevatlin*. Since
it creates problems for me, it's essentially one place and therefore you
can do ביטול bitul *bittul*.
So we have made שמואל *Shmuel* consistent.
Yes. So what שמואל *Shmuel* would say would not work is if
it's two חצרות *chatzerot* each one with one house. Then you couldn't
do ביטול bitul.
*bittul*, you have to do עירוב eiruv *eruv*, right? Oh well, that
what you do in that case we'll worry about when we get
to it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
okay, so גופא *gufa*, fine. So now we've figured out what שמואל
*Shmuel* said and how it's consistent with other statements of שמואל *Shmuel*.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* was sort of set back on
track and we've tried to be מדייק *medayek* from שמואל *Shmuel* that
this case of a non-Jew showing up wouldn't work with ביטול bitul,
*bittul*. Now let's get back to שמואל *Shmuel*'s statement. גופא *gufa*. So
אמר שמואל אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר Ein bittul reshush mechatzar l'chatzar.
ואין ביטול bitul רשות בחורבה *amar Shmuel ein bittul reshus m'chatzer l'chatzer
v'ein bittul reshus b'churba*. You don't have ביטול bittul רשות *bittul reshus*
from חצר *chatzer* to חצר *chatzer* and you don't have it in
a חורבה *churba*, completely different reasons although what both of these reflect
is that this ביטול bittul *bittul* is as I said some type
of a fiction and therefore we don't allow it across the board.
We have limits to when we can use it. רב יוחנן אמר
יש ביטול Bittul, רשות מחצר לחצר mechatzar lechatzar ויש ביטול Bittul. רשות
בחורבה *Rav Yochanan amar yesh bittul reshus m'chatzer l'chatzer v'yesh bittul reshus
b'churba*. He actually was less restrictive and as you see there's a
little letter by his two statements again reflecting that that's the הלכה
*halacha* and הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב *halacha k'divrei ha-meikel b'eruv*. Okay, but
he says no, we allow ביטול Bittul *bittul* in those cases. You
can do it in a backyard in a whatever back alley even
though it's not so needed and you can do it from one
courtyard to the next. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says וצריכא
*u'tzricha* and you need to tell me both cases. דאי אתמר מחצר
לחצר mechatzar lechatzar. בהא קאמר שמואל *d'i itmar m'chatzer l'chatzer b'ha ka-amar
Shmuel*, if you just say they're debating one courtyard to the next,
then I would say that's when שמואל *Shmuel* says we're not going
to allow it. That's going too far and it's not even so
needed because דהתם *d'hatam* והא תשמישתא לחווד והא תשמישתא לחווד vehacha tashmishta
lechud vehacha tashmishta lechud.
because look, in this case, if you wanted to do ביטול Bittul
from A to B, what would a scenario be? Let's take this
case where it's not creating a problem. You want to allow on
שבת B to carry their stuff into A. So all of A
is going to say on שבת we're מבטל mivatel our רשות to
you so now B can carry their stuff into A. That's not
so needed, right? They've got their courtyard, they've got their courtyard, you
know, and each one sort of uses their space separately, their separate
spaces. So there you would understand why שמואל would not, you know,
if you're going to put limits on ביטול, Bittul why שמואל would
not be happy in that case, because each one has its own
space, there's not such a need to do ביטול. Bittul והא תשמישתא
לחווד והא תשמישתא לחווד.
Each one has its own separate space to use, and again the
need is not great, and therefore we're not going to allow it.
אבל חורבה דתשמישתא חדא לתרביהו, aval churva detashmishta chada letarvayhu, but the
back alley that they both use equally together, it's a joint space,
it's more like a joint courtyard. אימא מודי ליה לרבי יוחנן, eima
modei lei leRabbi Yochanan, maybe he would concede the point to רבי
יוחנן that ביטול Bittul does work there. It's not as needed as
a courtyard, but it's more similar to the courtyard than the other
case. Okay, it's actually a shared space and therefore maybe ביטול Bittul
can work. וכי אתמר בהא אתמר, veki itmar beha itmar, and if
they just said they debated the case of the back alley, so
fine, I would have said בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן, beha ka'amar Rabbi
Yochanan, that's where רבי יוחנן says that it's okay. אבל בהך, aval
behach, but maybe these separate courtyards, מודי ליה לשמואל, modei lei leShmuel,
maybe he would admit to שמואל. צריכא, tzricha, you need both cases.
So now we have a nice opposed point to שמואל that is
much more liberal when it comes to the issues of ביטול Bittul
and does not need there to be such as great of a
need. I do want to point out again the point I said
before that the problem of מחצר לחצר mechatzar lechatzar,
could be expressed in two ways. One is just this ביטול Bittul
is a fiction so we want to limit it and we want
to limit it to cases where there are, you know, are sort
of the greatest need within one courtyard, not one courtyard to another.
But the other way of saying it is also the conceptual idea
of אוסרין osrin ומערבין מבטלין, that ביטול Bittul works if fundamentally we're
all one group anyway, then it's meaningful I can say, you know
what, I'm stepping, taking myself out of this. But if we're fundamentally
two separate groups, then that fiction of ביטול Bittul that's meaningful that
I say vis-a-vis you I'm מבטל mivatel my רשות is not so
meaningful because as opposed to when fundamentally we're already unified, the ביטול
Bittul then can be
more significant, you know, more meaningful. So it's not just maybe there's
a need for it, but it also works better in that case.
If I may we'll get to this later, so I still don't
understand how like I can show up in my hotel on שבת
and kind of go into the lobby there.
That has nothing to do with ביטול. Bittul That has to do
with, like I alluded to before, the fact that you're not really,
it's all basically owned by the hotel owner. So to the degree
that there's a חילוק רשויות chiluk reshuyos there, you know, basically there's
one person, it's really they can move you from one room to
the other if they don't like where you're where you are. Right.
So we can talk about that, but it's somewhat connected to the
גמרא Gemara before about the inn owner and his presence even when,
you know, even if there's a guy renting a room.
Okay. So, but these people where in an inn they did a
whole whatever it is they needed to do, so I guess they
couldn't have been moved to another room? Right.
So that yeah, that's a good point because then the גמרא Gemara
there sort of says, okay well you can rent something guy, what
do you have to rent one? Why don't you just say... Okay,
so we'll talk about that. And also the question is if it's
a Jewish, non-Jewish and so on. But just be, but yeah, it's
a good question and we'll get, you know, I'll try to get
back to that, okay? But let's finish up this point now and
move on. But it does connect to the גמרא Gemara we learned
at the end of yesterday. Okay. So now we have this issue.
רבי יוחנן is not bothered by any of this idea of מחצר
לחצר. mechatzar l'chatzar, שמואל is bothered מחצר לחצר, mechatzar l'chatzar. but according
to at least another statement of שמואל or רב יוסף's interpretation of
it, it depends whether אוסרין osrin. or not אוסרין. osrin In the
case where they create problems, it actually is considered one unit and
it works. When they don't create problems, in that case then it
is considered two units and that's where it doesn't work. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, הדר
אמר שמואל אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר, hadra amar Shmuel ein bitul
reshus mechatzar lechatzar, when שמואל said you can't go from one courtyard
to the next to do a ביטול, לא אמרן אלא בשתי חצרות
שפתח אחד ביניהן, lo amaran ela bishte chatzeros shepetach echad beneihen, so
he's saying what we just said. That's only when their courtyards are,
yes they are, you can access one to the other, but basically
they have separate access to the רשות הרבים reshus harabim so they're
not unified. אבל בשתי חצרות זו לפנים מזו, aval bishte chatzeros zo
lifnim mizo, but this should not be this is a repeat from
what we said before, two courtyards one inside the other, היכי שאוסרין
מבטלין, heichei she'osrin mevatlin, because here A creates problems on B and
if A sits out B can't carry. In that case, if somebody
and they can actually do ביטול one courtyard to the next because
if אוסרין ומערבין מבטלין. So אביי Abaye is saying back what we
said until now. But notice by the way, who said it? אביי
Abaye said it, right? This is actually a fascinating גמרא. On the
עמוד א', who said this idea, מקום שאוסרין ומערבין מבטלין? makom she'osrin
umearvin mevatlin? Right? That was quoted in the name of שמואל. דאמר
שמואל De-amar Shmuel: כל מקום שאוסרין ומערבין מבטלין. kol makom she'osrin u'm'arvin
m'vatlin, Then on the עמוד ב', amud beis, you had, you know...
אביי Abaye reminding רב יוסף that רב יוסף had said it in
the name of שמואל. Then by the bottom of the עמוד ב',
amud beis, you have אביי Abaye saying it. So since שמואל hadn't
directly said it and רב יוסף is no longer taking credit for
having said it, now we have אביי Abaye being the one who
is saying it. So it's almost like a reverse מסורה mesorah here.
Okay, so now אביי Abaye is the one that's saying it. So
now and to show you the contrast, רבא Rava disagrees. So the
גמרא says,
where was... רבא אומר אפילו שתי חצירות זו לפנים מזו, Rava omer
afilu shtei chatzeiros zu lifnim mizu, even this case, one inside of
the other,
פעמים מבטלין ופעמים אין מבטלין. pa’amim mevatlin upa’amim ein mevatlin. You can't
always do ביטול from A to B. Okay. Basically when שמואל said
you can't do ביטול מחצר לחצר, bittul mechatzar lechatzar, it's not with
this big difference between this case and this case. Even in this
case where it's אוסרין and they create a problem, even in that
case you mostly cannot
do ביטול from one חצר to the next. And now he's going
to explain the different scenarios. כיצד? keitzad?
Okay, so let's take a look. פעמים ופעמים אין מבטלין, pa’amim upa’amim
ein mevatlin, כיצד. keitzad. נתנו עירובן בחיצונה ושכח אחד, nosnu eiruvon bachitzona
veshachach echad,
now what you have to understand, let's back up a little on
this, what you have to understand is that if A and B
want to make a joint,
if they want to make a joint עירוב, eiruv. how do they
do it? Okay, so the way you do it as we sort
of mentioned before is that you go ahead and you take, second,
there's the... Okay anyway,
so anyway, if they want to go ahead and make a joint
עירוב, eiruv... then A makes their own עירוב, Eruv they all do
it, the עירוב Eruv of A and you've got the עירוב, Eruv
they each make their own עירוב, Eruv, okay, and then you take
one of the עירובין eiruvin from one and you deposit it in
the other courtyard, right? So you can do it either way. Okay,
so we're going to talk about those two scenarios based on where
was the עירוב Eruv, put and which was the person that forgot
to participate? Okay, and that's going to make the difference. So let's
take a look. כיצד. keitzad. נתנו עירובן בחיצונה. nosnu eiruvon bachitzona.
So you went ahead and you put the joint עירוב Eruv. in
the outer one. We'll call that A, okay, the עירוב Eruv, of...
You put the joint עירוב Eruv. in the outer one.
Okay. נתנו עירובן בחיצונה. nosnu eiruvon bachitzona. ושכח אחד בין מן הפנימית
ובין מן החיצונה, veshachach echad bein min hapnimis uvein min hachitzona,
one of the people either in A or in B forgot, ולא
עירב, velo eirev, and didn't make the עירוב. Eruv. שתיהן אסורות, shteihan
asuros, there's no way to solve it, they're both forbidden. נתנו עירובן
בפנימית. nosnu eiruvon bapnimis. You put the joint עירוב Eruv in the
inner one. ושכח אחד מן הפנימית ולא עירב. veshachach echad min hapnimis
velo eirev. So if one of the inner people forgot, we're going
to unpack this and explain it in a minute. If one of
the inner people forgot and didn't make an עירוב, Eruv, שתיהן אסורות,
shteihan asuros, they're both forbidden,
no way to solve it. שכח אחד מן החיצונה ולא עירב. shachach
echad min hachitzona velo eirev.
Here's the one case that it would work. If you put it
in the inside and one of the guys on the outside forgot,
פנימית מותרת pnimis muteres וחיצונה אסורה. vechitzona asura. The inner one is
permitted and the outer one is forbidden. So now we have to
unpack this. So let me, let me basically just tell you the
one case that works and conceptually why it works in a simple
way and then we're going to read through the גמרא. If you
put the עירוב, Eruv נתנו עירוב, nosnu eiruv, in the outer one...
Wait was that the last case?
No, you put the עירוב Eruv in the inner. The one case
that works is is that if the joint עירוב Eruv, is here
and the problem is created by somebody in B, somebody in B
forgot, that's the problem, right? So then A can at least carry
because then you guys are the problem, we have the עירוב, Eruv
forget about you. Okay, we'll just basically, as the גמרא says, close
our door and consider ourselves off by ourselves. Okay, so that's the
case that actually does work.
What would that mean, B would work then?
That A can carry within A's space itself.
But is there always even carry... Aren't there three עירובין here? There's
עירוב Eruv A, there's עירוב Eruv B, and then there's עירוב Eruv
joint.
Yeah, yeah, one minute.
This might be, one minute, that they did not... Hold on a
minute. נתנו עירובן
בפנימית ושכח אחד מן הפנימית
ולא עירב שתיהן אסורות. nosnu eiruvon
bapnimis veshachach echad min hapnimis velo
eirev shteihan asuros.
Hold on a minute.
No, presumably, I'm sorry, so presumably,
you're right that one minute. So the question is why would B...
Yeah, the point is like this. You're right, I'm sorry. One courtyard
made an עירוב, Eruv, it's not... I misstated it. I misstated it,
I'm sorry. One courtyard made an עירוב Eruv, and put the עירוב
Eruv, in the other courtyard. Okay, the other courtyard didn't bother making
the עירוב. Eruv, Okay, so basically you even took, you know, you
basically took the עירוב... Eruv, A and you brought it over to
B, or these guys made the עירוב Eruv and they brought it
over to A. One of those things happened, but you're right, there's
only one עירוב Eruv here. Okay? So if that one עירוב is
put in as—is here, is here, then B is creating the problem,
okay, and they are a problem because now they've all have one
עירוב, they're all jointly together in this one עירוב, and somebody here
isn't part of the עירוב. So somebody's not part of the עירוב,
they create a problem, right? Somebody forgot. In that case, you can
just ignore B and we still holding on to the עירוב. That's
the one case that actually works. But any other scenario won't work,
and now let's see the גמרא explain why. Now it's not only
you need ביטול, right? You could say, so fine, that has to
do with ביטול. Just ignore B and we keep the עירוב. Right.
Okay, but let's take a look at how the גמרא explains why
it doesn't work.
This עירוב joint is members of A and members of B getting
together and putting...
Yeah, I mean the way רש״י Rashi explains what actually happened is
that one of them put—did the עירוב, and they—that made it for
that court, and they brought it to the other courtyard and that
sort of then became part of the עירוב for the other courtyard.
All of members of B or basically—all of members of B and
all of members of A getting together from each one of these
four houses or...
No, only one courtyard gets together and by putting it in the
other, they bring the other into it.
He represents these—representative of all the all the B primes or whatever
it is, and he says, "I'm gonna take my own מצה matzah
but I'm doing it on all of your behalf," right? They need
to all chip in and put in like a...
Yeah, let's not—I mean, again, if you need more of the details,
I can get it to you, but let's just not over-worry about
that right now. So let's see what the גמרא says. Okay, so
now we're gonna unpack it.
So where are we? נתנו עירובן בחיצונה ושכח אחד בין מן הפנימית
בין מן החיצונית. Nitnu Eiruvin b'chitzona v'shachach echad ben min hapnimis ben
min hachitzona.
If in the outer courtyard, the עירוב was put in the outer
courtyard, and then whoever forgot, whether an inner or an outer person,
ולא עירב v'lo Eirev and did not part of the עירוב, שתיהן
אסורות. shehna asurot. They're both forbidden. Why? Here's why they're both forbidden.
האי בר פנימית למאן ליבטל? Hai bar pnimis l'man livatel? So let's
look.
The way the case is is that the עירוב was put—the joint
עירוב was put out in B. Okay, that's where the joint עירוב
is. And there it's gonna say you're stuck. Why are you stuck?
Let's say the guy who forgot was A. Now remember, A creates—by—A
automatically creates problems for B because they go through B, so A
is considered to be present in B. And one of the guys
in A forgot. So now he's creating a problem. So what can
he do? He can maybe do ביטול to get himself out of
the picture. That's how we'll try to solve it. Okay, so האי
בר פנימית למאן ליבטל? Hai bar pnimis l'man livatel? Who is he
going to do ביטול to? ליבטל לבני פנימית? Livatel l'vnei pnimis? לית
ליה עירובא גבייהו. Lessa lei Eiruva gabaihu. Let's say he says,
"Hey guys, I'm מבטל mivatel to you guys." Okay, but that doesn't
help. That maybe means that this is okay, but this can't actually
be considered okay by itself because the עירוב isn't here. We can
only actually be considered okay if we're looking at ourselves as an
entire unit. So doing the ביטול to you doesn't work because in
order for us to get the benefits of the עירוב, we have
to see ourselves joint with B. So your ביטול can't only be
to us, your ביטול has to be also to the people of
B. So that's the next solution. So ליבטל לבני חיצונית? livatel l'vnei
chitzona? אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר. Ein bittul reshush mechatzar l'chatzar.
That's the principle that you can't do ביטול from one חצר to
the other even when you create a problem on the other. Remember,
this is the more restrictive view of שמואל, that even in this
scenario you can't do ביטול from A to B even though A
creates a problem for B. So that's why that doesn't work when
one of the inner guys forgot. Now let's say an outer guy
forgot in the same case. האי בר חיצונית למאן ליבטל? Hai bar
chitzona l'man livatel? Who is he gonna do ביטול to? If one
of the B's forgot to join in. ליבטל לבני חיצונית? Livatel l'vnei
chitzona? If it's his own courtyard, איכא פנימית דאסרו עליה. ika pnimis
d'asru alei. So he says to the guys, "Look, I know I
didn't make an עירוב, I'm making problems, I'm waiving my rights, I'm
מבטל." Okay, if it was just B, that'd be great, we have
the עירוב, we can get the benefits of the עירוב, you've מבטל
to us, we're safe. But no, I can't ignore A! Even though
I got the עירוב, I can't ignore A because they go through
us. So A perforce is part of our group. So in order
for my ביטול to be meaningful, I have to be מבטל to
A as well. But then we have the same problem. Okay? ליבטל
לבני פנימית? Livatel l'vnei pnimis? אין ביטול רשות מחצר לחצר. mechatzar l'chatzar,
But I can't be מבטל back to A because I can't go
from חצר to חצר. So this case, basically neither case works because
these guys have to include A because A goes through them, okay,
and so therefore they have
to do a ביטול מחצר לחצר, and these guys have to include
B because B has the עירוב and therefore if they had to
do a ביטול it would have to be מחצר לחצר. So in
this case it doesn't work because the ביטול would have to be
מחצר לחצר, which will not work. Now how about when the עירוב
is in A?
That, as I've already pointed out to you, is gonna have one—one
solution.
So okay, נתנו עירובן בפנימית ושכח אחד מן הפנימית... nathan Eiruvin bapnimis
v'shachach echad min hapnimis... So if one of the guys on the
inside forgot, שהן אסורות *she-en assurot*, then you got a problem. Why?
האי בפנימית למאן יבטל *hai bapnimis leman yevatel*? Who's he going to
do ביטול *bitul* to? לבטל לפני הפנימית *levatel lifnei hapnimis* to his
own guys, so איכא חיצונה דאסרה עליה *ika chitzona de-asra aleih*. So
again, if you talked about this you would say not a problem,
just do ביטול *bitul*, you guys have the עירוב *eruv*, you're all
fine. No, since B is part of their עירוב *eruv*, the very
fact that they joined into the עירוב *eruv* means that you can't
ignore them. So that you have to do ביטול *bitul* to B
as well because B is part of this whole joint עירוב *eruv*,
but then that's ביטול מחצר לחצר *bitul michatzar lechatzar*. So לבטל לפני
חיצונה *levatel
lifnei chitzona*, so do ביטול *bitul* to B as well, אין ביטול
רשות מחצר לחצר *ein bitul reshus michatzar lechatzar*, you can't go ביטול
*bitul* from one to the other. Now so the only case that
works is if a B guy forgot. Why does that work? It's
still true that B is part of A, so the B guy
forgetting he shouldn't be able to do a ביטול *bitul* to A,
again, they're all together, they all have the same עירוב *eruv*, but
the reason it works is שכח אחד מן החיצונה ולא עירב *shachach
echad min hachitzona velo eirev*, that case, פנימית מותרת *pnimis muteres*, the
inner one is permissible, דאחד דשא ומשתמשא *de-achad dasha umishtamsha*, it slams
its door and uses its space. Okay, וחיצונה אסורה *vechitzona asura*, and
the outer one is forbidden. So basically, because they've all joined in
the עירוב *eruv* and because A goes through B, they're almost always
considered to be all big one unit, that's on the negative side.
Okay, I mean they're one unit, but you can't solve it because
אין ביטול מחצר לחצר *ein bitul michatzar lechatzar*. Okay, that's the more
restrictive read of שמואל *Shmuel*. That even though it's אוסרין *osrin*, they
still can't do ביטול *bitul*. Okay, so because they're all one unit
even because of the עירוב *eruv* where the עירוב *eruv* is, they
all joined in the עירוב *eruv* where they go through, you've got
a problem. The one case that works is when
a guy in B forgot and the עירוב *eruv* is in A.
Because since a guy in B forgot, you don't need them to
do ביטול *bitul*. Okay, and you could just say you're the problem,
you're the problem, who needs you, get out of here. Okay, so
if a guy in A forgot, we can't say get out of
here, we need ביטול *bitul*. Because you're with that space, and the
ביטול *bitul* then has to include the other members of the עירוב
*eruv* and that's the problem, אין ביטול מחצר לחצר *ein bitul michatzar
lechatzar*. But in this case, we can just say forget about you
and we're totally okay and A is fine. Okay, so that's actually
the situation that works. Now the problem is that works, it seems
to be, not the problem, but it seems to be working without
ביטול *bitul*. Exactly. So why do we say that this is the
case that ביטול *bitul* works? Where is the ביטול *bitul*? So רשי
*Rashi* says, if you take a look at the first רשי *Rashi*,
we'll end with this, top of סז עמוד א *samech zayin amud
aleph*, דהא מודה שמואל דמבטלי בני חיצונה לבני פנימית אותה רשות שבאה
להן לתוכן על ידי הרגל עירובן *de-ha modeh Shmuel de-mevatlei benei chitzona
livnei pnimis osah reshus she-ba-ah lahen letochan al yedei hergel eruvon*. That
basically the only ביטול *bitul* that B does to A is B
withdraws its right to the עירוב *eruv*. B says we are מוחל
*mochel* on the עירוב *eruv*, and that allows A to use the
עירוב *eruv* just for itself. Okay, and that's the case that it
works. Alright, but any other, and they're not really doing ביטול מחצר
לחצר *bitul michatzar lechatzar*, we're not somehow giving you rights in our
חצר *chatzar* or whatever, that would be a problem. We're just withdrawing
our right to the עירוב *eruv*, and because you can just seal
us off, that actually makes it acceptable. Alright, but if one of
the guys in A forgot, okay, it doesn't, B again, that's not
going to solve the problem because since B is part of the
עירוב *eruv* and they're not where the problem is, there's no real
solution in that case. Alright, so more of this fun discussion tomorrow.